Rutgers Department of Linguistics 18 Seminary Place New Brunswick, New Jersey 08901-1184 www.linkedin.com/in/yu-cao-pdiacos yc825@linguistics.rutgers.edu

PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

Linguistics

Ph.D. student in linguistics specialized in computational linguistics, semantics, syntaxsemantics interface, and discourse analysis. Strong critical-thinking and problem-solving skills.

Computation 10+ years of experiences in algorithms and data structure. The First Prize in National Olympiad in Informatics in Provinces 2007, China.

NLP/NLU

Research in how formal theories contribute to robust natural language processing. Coursework: NLU and Computational Semantics, Project Seminar: Linguistic Knowledge in Reusable Sentence Encoders at NYU. Graph formalisms for meaning representations at NASSLLI 2018, CMU. Statistical NLP (Coursera), Machine Learning (Coursera), Introduction to Deep Learning (Coursera), Bayesian Methods for Machine Learning (Coursera).

EXPERIENCE

• Ontology Linguist Intern

08/2019-10/2019

Assistant Cross-Functional Group, Facebook (via PRO Unlimited)

Prototyped models towards universal semantic dependency + ontology approach to cross-domain semantic parsing using PyTorch. Automated inferences and sub-ontology extraction in OWL 2 ontology knowledge graphs using Python.

• Teaching Assistant/Course Instructor

09/2018-08/2020

Linguistics Department, Rutgers University

Courses taught: Introduction to Linguistic Theory, Invented Languages.

Research Assistant

12/2014-07/2015

Center for Sign Linguistics and Deaf Studies, CUHK

Provided linguistic expertise and assisted in developing a Chinese grammatical knowledge assessment software for deaf/hard of hearing children.

EDUCATION

• Ph.D. in Linguistics

2016-present

Rutgers University-New Brunswick

• M.A. in Chinese Linguistics and Language Acquisition

• B.A. in Teaching Chinese as a Foreign Language

2013-2014

The Chinese University of Hong Kong Dean's List. Best M.A. Thesis Award

2009-2013

Sichuan Normal University, China

Distinguished Thesis Award

PUBLICATIONS

- Automated Fact-Value Distinction in Court Opinions
 European Journal of Law and Economics. With Daniel Chen and Elliot Ash.

 Automated classification of fact vs. value statements in written judicial decisions. Showed in application that the value segments are more informative of the ideological direction of U.S. circuit court opinions.
- Investigating BERT's Knowledge of Language: Five Analysis Methods with NPIs
 Proceedings of EMNLP 2019. Equal contribution with Sam Bowman and 14 other authors.

 Team role: constructed and conducted the main transfer learning experiments.

PROJECTS

- Graph Representation of Meaning
 Designed a graph based semantic representation that encodes plurality and quantification in natural language. Defined its model-theoretical interpreter. Developed a CCG-based graph construction mechanism (semantic parser).
- Incremental topological sorting
 Designed algorithms for topological sorting under uncertain precedence conditions. Experimented with dynamic updating strategies that significantly improve on static topological sorting in time complexity.

SKILLS

Machine learning modeling in NLP Linguistic data analysis Python, C, Matlab, PyTorch, Tensorflow, Scikit-learn Statistics

LANGUAGES

Mandarin (native), English (fluent), Japanese (working fluency; certified JLPT Level N1), Cantonese (limited fluency), French (beginner), Hong Kong Sign Language (beginner).